Williams Obstetrics.
Chapter 15: Normal and Abnormal Fetal Anatomy.
Biometry Brain And Spine Head, Face, And Neck Thorax Heart Gastrointestinal Obstruction Ventral Wall Defects Kidneys And Genitourinary Tract Skeleton References The ability to detect and characterize abnormalities before birth is one of the marvels of modern obstetrics.
Sonography can image the fetus with remarkable precision.
Components of the standard anatomic survey are listed in Table 15-1.
These have been termed essential elements by the American College of Obstetricians and Gynecologists (2020) and minimal elements by the American Institute of Ultrasound in Medicine (2018).
Ideally, residency training in Obstetrics and Gynecology includes education in acquisition and interpretation of these views.
Resources provided by national societies assist with this endeavor .
Table 15-1.
Components of Standard and Detailed Anatomic Surveys A detailed fetal anatomic survey is a specialized examination that may include more than 60 components, each determined on a case-by-case basis.
It is the primary method of evaluating at-risk pregnancies and characterizing fetal abnormalities, thereby aiding consultation and delivery planning.
Indications are shown in Table 14-6 and discussed further in Chapter 14 (p. 251).
At Parkland hospital, the detailed survey includes, at minimum, an attempt to visualize all components required by the American Institute of Ultrasound in Medicine for normal detailed case submission .
This chapter presents the standard and detailed anatomic surveys and some of the many fetal abnormalities that may be detected when visualization is optimal.
When imaging or measuring any fetal structure, care should be taken to place the focal zone at the appropriate level and to magnify the image appropriately .
Whenever a fetal abnormality is identified, a detailed anatomic survey is recommended.
With rare exception, amniocentesis with chromosomal microarray analysis also is offered.
If a cardiac abnormality is identified, fetal echocardiography is indicated.
Additional indications for these specialized examinations and for fetal magnetic resonance (MR) imaging are reviewed in Chapter 14.
Biometry.
In the first trimester, crown-rump length (CRL) measurement is used to establish or confirm gestational age (Appendix, p. 1234).
The earlier that sonography is performed, the more accurate this estimation.
Gestational age assessment is reviewed in Chapter 14 (p. 248).
The fetus is imaged in the midsagittal plane in a neutral, nonflexed position so that its length can be measured in a straight line .
The average of three measurements is used.
First-trimester nuchal translucency measurement is reviewed in Chapter 14 (p. 249).
Figure 15-1.
The crown-rump length measures 61 mm in this 12-week, 4-day fetus.
In the second and third trimesters, the biparietal diameter, head circumference, abdominal circumference, and femur length are measured to confirm gestational age, if not already established in the first trimester, and to estimate fetal weight.
Ultrasound equipment and report packages calculate these estimates using standardized nomograms .
If an abnormality involving one of the parameters is suspected, consideration is given to excluding it from the gestational age calculation.
Fetal weight nomograms are available that do not include the head measurements or the femur measurement (Hadlock, 1984; Shepard, 1982).
The biparietal diameter and head circumference are measured in the transthalamic view.
This is a transverse image that includes the midline falx cerebri, cavum septum pellucidum, thalami, and insula (Fig. 15-2A).
The cerebral hemispheres should appear symmetric, and the cerebellum should not be visible.
The biparietal diameter is measured perpendicular to the falx cerebri, from the outer edge of the skull in the near field to the inner edge of the skull in the far field.
The head circumference is measured by placing an ellipse around the outer edge of the skull.
The head circumference may also be calculated by averaging the biparietal diameter and the
occipito-frontal diameter and multiplying by π. Figure 15-2.
Normal biometry.
A. Transthalamic view depicts measurement of the biparietal diameter (BPD) and head circumference (HC).
Landmarks include the cavum septum pellucidum (CSP), thalami (T), and insula (I).
B. Abdominal circumference view (AC) shows measurement and landmarks, which include the stomach (S) and the confluence of the umbilical vein (U) and the left portal vein.
C. Femur length measurement (FL).
The abdominal circumference is measured in a transverse image that includes the stomach and the J-shaped confluence of the umbilical vein with the portal sinus.
An ellipse is placed just outside the fetal skin edge (Fig. 152B).
The image should appear as round as possible and ideally contain no more than 1 rib on either side.
The spine should be visible in cross-section at the 3 o’clock or 9 o’clock position, whereas the kidneys should not be visible, as they are lower in the abdomen.
Abdominal circumference is the biometric parameter most affected by fetal growth.
An abdominal circumference below the 10th percentile may be used to diagnose fetalgrowth restriction .
The femur length is measured with the ultrasound beam perpendicular to the long axis of the shaft.
Calipers are placed at each end of the calcified diaphysis (Fig. 15-2C).
Throughout the second and third trimesters, the femur length to abdominal circumference ratio is normally 20 to 24 percent.
If this ratio is below 18 percent, a skeletal dysplasia should be considered, particularly if other long-bone measurements are lagging (p. 302).
As discussed in Chapter 17 (p. 340), a mildly foreshortened femur length measurement is also a minor marker for Down syndrome .
Various nomograms exist for other fetal structures, including the transverse cerebellar diameter, ocular distances, nasal bone, ear length, jaw index, thoracic circumference, and lengths of the liver, kidneys, long bones, and feet.
They may be used to address specific questions regarding organ system abnormalities, congenital infection, or genetic syndromes (Appendix, pp. 1238–1241).
Brain And Spine.
Standard sonographic evaluation of the fetal brain includes three transverse (axial) views.
As noted, the transthalamic view should contain the midline falx cerebri, cavum septum pellucidum (CSP), thalami, and insula (see Fig. 15-2A).
The CSP is the space between the two laminae that separate the frontal horns of the lateral ventricles.
It should be visible between approximately 17 and 37 weeks’ gestation, but after this, fusion of the septi pellucidi may obliterate the cavum.
Inability to visualize a normal CSP may indicate a midline brain abnormality .
For example, the frontal horns are widely spaced apart in agenesis of the corpus callosum (ACC), whereas in cases of septo-optic dysplasia (de Morsier syndrome) and lobar holoprosencephaly, the frontal horns communicate.
Discussed in Chapter 16 (p. 312), an abnormally wide CSP may also be found with trisomy 18.
Figure 15-3.
Absence of the cavum septum pellucidum, with coronal (A) and transverse (B) images showing communication between the frontal horns (FH) of the lateral ventricles.
This may be isolated but can occur in the setting of septo-optic dysplasia or lobar holoprosencephaly.
C = choroid plexus; F = falx cerebri.
The transventricular view lies superior to the transthalamic view and, as the name implies, includes the lateral ventricles.
The ventricles are measured at their atrium, which is the confluence of the temporal and occipital horns .
The measurement is normally 5 to 9 mm throughout the second and third trimesters.
Cerebrospinal fluid is produced within the ventricles by the choroid plexus.
Choroid plexus cysts are present in 0.5 to 2 percent of uncomplicated pregnancies and approximately 30 to 50 percent of pregnancies with trisomy 18 (Fig. 16-5, p. 312) .
A detailed ultrasound examination is generally offered when found.
In the absence of an associated ultrasound abnormality, or unless an aneuploidy screening test indicates increased risk for trisomy 18, a choroid
plexus cyst is considered a normal variant.
Figure 15-4.
Transventricular view.
A. Transverse image of the lateral ventricles, which contain the choroid plexus (C).
B. The ventricles are measured at the atria (A), the confluence of the temporal and occipital horns.
The measurement is normally 5–9 mm. Vp = lateral ventricle.
Reproduced with permission from Rosa Robles, RDMS.
For the transcerebellar view, the transducer is angled back through the posterior fossa .
Structures visible in this image include the midline falx cerebri, cavum septum pellucidum, thalami, cerebellum, and cisterna magna.
The cerebellum and cisterna magna are measured, and between 15 and 20 weeks’ gestation, the nuchal skinfold thickness also is measured.
From 15 until 22 weeks, the cerebellar diameter in millimeters is roughly equivalent to the gestational age in weeks .
Cerebellar hypoplasia has been associated with various central nervous system (CNS) and non-CNS abnormalities .
The cisterna magna should measure between 2 and 10 mm throughout the second trimester and may reach 12 mm in the latter part of the third trimester.
It becomes effaced when the Chiari II malformation is present (p. 277).
If the cisterna magna is enlarged, the differential diagnosis includes absence of all or part of the vermis (p. 279), a cyst such as an arachnoid cyst within the posterior fossa, or mega-cisterna magna, which is a diagnosis of exclusion and has an excellent prognosis.
An increased nuchal skinfold measurement is associated with increased risk for Down syndrome, other genetic syndromes, and structural abnormalities .
Figure 15-5.
Transcerebellar view.
A. Transverse image of the posterior fossa showing measurement of the cerebellum (Cereb), cisterna magna (CM), and nuchal skinfold thickness (NF).
B. Third-trimester image depicting the cerebellar hemispheres (CH) and cerebellar vermis (V).
The fourth ventricle (4) is anterior to the vermis.
CSP = cavum septum pellucidum; I = insula; P = cerebral peduncles.
Imaging of the spine includes evaluation of the cervical, thoracic, lumbar, and sacral regions .
Representative images are often obtained in the sagittal or coronal plane.
However, imaging of each spinal segment in the transverse plane is more sensitive for anomaly detection.
Transverse images demonstrate three ossification centers.
The anterior ossification center is the vertebral body, and the posterior paired ossification centers represent the junction of vertebral laminae and pedicles.
Ossification of the spine proceeds in a cranial-caudal fashion.
The ossification of the upper sacrum (S1-S2) is not generally visible before 16 weeks’ gestation, and ossification of the entire sacrum may not be visible until 21 weeks .
Thus, detection of some spinal abnormalities can be challenging in the early second trimester.
Figure 15-6.
Normal fetal spine.
This sagittal image depicts the cervical (C), thoracic (T), lumbar (L), and sacral spine (S).
Arrows denote the parallel rows of paired posterior ossification centers, which represent the junction of vertebral lamina and pedicles.
# Neural-tube Defects.
These defects include anencephaly, myelomeningocele (spina bifida), cephalocele, and rare spinal dysraphisms.
Normally, the neural tube closes by the embryonic age of 26 to 28 days .
The birth prevalence of neural-tube defects approximates 0.9 in 1000 in the United States and most of Europe and 1.3 in 1000 in the United Kingdom (Cragan, 2009; Dolk, 2010).
Many neural-tube defects can be prevented with folic acid supplementation.
When isolated, neural-tube defect inheritance is multifactorial, and the recurrence risk without periconceptional folic acid supplementation is 3 to 5 percent .
Screening for neural-tube defects may be performed with either ultrasound alone or ultrasound in addition to maternal serum alphafetoprotein (MSAFP) level measurement .
Between 15 and 20 weeks’ gestation, an upper MSAFP threshold of 2.5 multiples of the median (MoM) is anticipated to detect 95 percent with fetal anencephaly and 80 percent with myelomeningocele.
However,
detection with standard sonography is at least comparable to that with MSAFP (Dashe, 2006; Norem 2005).
A detailed ultrasound examination is the preferred diagnostic test and may identify other abnormalities or conditions that also elevate MSAFP levels (Table 17-5, p. 338).
Anencephaly is an absence of the cranium and telencephalon above the level of the skull base and orbits .
Acrania is absence of the cranium with protrusion of disorganized brain tissue, and herniation of the latter tissue is exencephaly.
Importantly, brain tissue visible in the late first trimester is often not seen when ultrasound is performed in the second or third trimester.
Thus, anencephaly is the final stage of exencephaly.
It is often diagnosed in the late first trimester, and with adequate visualization, virtually all cases may be diagnosed in the second trimester.
Figure 15-7.
Anencephaly/acrania.
A. This transabdominal image at 11 weeks’ gestation depicts relatively subtle absence of the cranium.
B. A transvaginal image at 11 weeks demonstrates more clearly the protrusion of a disorganized mass of brain tissue.
C. By 14 weeks, this tissue resembles a “shower cap.
CRL = crown–rump length.
Sonographically, the cranial contour may appear abnormal in the first trimester and may resemble a “shower cap” in the late first or early second trimester.
The face often appears triangular, and sagittal images demonstrate lack of an ossified cranium.
Hydramnios from impaired fetal swallowing is common in the third trimester.
Anencephaly is uniformly lethal.
If the pregnancy is continued, perinatal palliative care consultation should be considered .
Cephalocele is the herniation of meninges through a cranial defect, typically located in the midline occipital region .
When brain tissue herniates through the skull defect, the anomaly is termed an encephalocele.
Herniation of the cerebellum and other posterior fossa structures constitutes a Chiari III malformation.
Microcephaly is common by the third trimester.
Associated intracranial abnormalities are frequently visible, and survivors have a high incidence of neurological deficits and intellectual disability.
Cephalocele is an important feature of the autosomal recessive Meckel-Gruber syndrome, which includes cystic renal dysplasia and polydactyly.
A cephalocele not located in the occipital midline raises suspicion for amnionic-band sequence .
Figure 15-8.
Encephalocele.
This transverse image depicts a large defect in the occipital region of the cranium (arrows) through which meninges and brain tissue have herniated.
Spina bifida is characterized by defects in the vertebrae, typically the dorsal arches, and subsequent exposure of the meninges and nerve roots.
The prevalence approximates 1 in 2000 births (Cragan, 2009; Dolk, 2010).
Herniation of a meningeal sac and neural elements is a myelomeningocele (Fig. 15-9A).
Less commonly, only an empty meningeal sac herniates, which is a meningocele.
Transverse images are helpful to demonstrate separation or splaying of the lateral processes and characterize the level of the defect.
Most cases are open spina bifida, which means that the defect includes skin and soft tissues.
Closed defects are skin-covered and more challenging to detect prenatally.
Figure 15-9.
Myelomeningocele.
A. Sagittal image of a lumbosacral myelomeningocele.
Arrowheads indicate nerve roots within the anechoic herniated sac.
The overlying skin abruptly stops at the defect (arrow).
B. Transthalamic image demonstrating flattening of the frontal bones (arrows)—the lemon sign.
C. Transcerebellar image depicting the banana sign, an anterior curvature of the cerebellum (arrows) and effacement of the cisterna magna.
Detection of spina bifida is aided by two characteristic cranial findings .
Flatting or scalloping of the frontal bones is termed the “lemon sign,” and anterior curvature of the cerebellum with effacement of the cisterna magna is the “banana sign” (Fig. 15-9B,C).
These findings are manifestations of the Arnold-Chiari or Chiari II malformation.
This develops when
downward displacement of the spinal cord pulls a portion of the cerebellum through the foramen magnum and into the upper cervical canal.
The biparietal diameter measurement often lags behind the other biometric parameters.
Ventriculomegaly is common after mid-gestation, and 80 to 90 percent of infants with myelomeningocele require ventriculoperitoneal shunt placement (Adzick 2011, Chao, 2010).
Affected children require multidisciplinary care to address problems related to the defect such as deficits in swallowing, bladder and bowel function, and ambulation.
Fetal myelomeningocele surgery is discussed in Chapter 19 (p. 372).
# Ventriculomegaly.
Distention of the lateral ventricles is considered a nonspecific marker of abnormal brain development .
Mild ventriculomegaly is diagnosed when the atrial width measures 10 to 12 mm; moderate ventriculomegaly, when the measurement is 13 to 15 mm; and severe ventriculomegaly when >15 mm .
Representative images are depicted in Figure 15-10.
The choroid plexus may appear dangling in severe cases.
Figure 15-10.
Ventriculomegaly.
A. Mild ventriculomegaly.
The atria measured 11 mm.
No associated abnormality or underlying etiology was identified.
B. Severe ventriculomegaly.
In this fetus with aqueductal stenosis, the atria measured 45 mm. Arrow denotes the dangling choroid plexus.
Ventriculomegaly may occur secondary to a variety of central nervous system abnormalities and is associated with numerous genetic and infectious etiologies.
Initial evaluation includes a detailed examination of fetal anatomy, amniocentesis for chromosomal microarray analysis, and testing for congenital infections such as cytomegalovirus and toxoplasmosis .
Genetic syndromes resulting in ventriculomegaly include L1 Xlinked aqueductal stenosis, Joubert syndrome, Walker Warburg syndrome, hydrolethalus syndrome, and lissencephaly syndromes .
Ventriculomegaly does not typically result in significant skull enlargement.
Two exceptions—when macrocrania often occurs—are aqueductal stenosis and the asymmetric ventriculomegaly interhemispheric cyst callosal dysgenesis (AVID) syndrome .
Fetal MR imaging should be considered to assess for associated abnormalities that may not be detectable sonographically (Herrera, 2020a; Katz, 2018) .
Prognosis is determined by etiology, severity, and progression.
In a systematic review of nearly 1500 mild to moderate cases, 1 to 2 percent were associated with congenital infection; 5 percent, with aneuploidy; and 12 percent, with neurological abnormality .
With chromosomal microarray analysis, genetic abnormalities may be identified in 10 to 15 percent .
The larger the atria, the greater the likelihood of an underlying CNS abnormality and subsequent abnormal outcome (Gaglioti, 2009; Joó, 2008).
If ventriculomegaly is isolated and remains mild, development is normal in at least 90 percent, and if moderate, development is normal in at least 75 percent .
Progression significantly raises the likelihood of abnormal neurological development.
# Agenesis of the Corpus Callosum.
The corpus callosum is a major fiber bundle that connects reciprocal regions of the cerebral hemispheres.
It is best viewed in the midsagittal plane, and color Doppler may demonstrate the pericallosal artery .
Agenesis of the corpus callosum has characteristic sonographic findings.
The frontal horns are widely separated, and the occipital horns are rounded— which is called colpocephaly.
Together these findings give the lateral ventricles a teardrop shape .
A normal cavum septum pellucidum is not visible because of frontal horn displacement.
In the midline, bundles of Probst represent fiber tracts that no longer cross in the midline.
Ventriculomegaly is not uncommon, and without the corpus callosum bordering the third ventricle superiorly, the third ventricle may be elevated and mildly enlarged.
Figure 15-11.
Normal corpus callosum.
A. Arrows point to the corpus callosum in this midsagittal image.
B. Power Doppler image of the pericallosal artery (arrowheads).
Figure 15-12.
Agenesis of the corpus callosum.
A. This
transverse image demonstrates a teardropshaped ventricle.
The frontal horns (F) are widely separated, no cavum septum pellucidum is visible, and bundles of Probst (P) line the midline.
B. There is mild ventriculomegaly, no cavum septum pellucidum is visible (arrow), and the third ventricle (3V) is elevated and enlarged.
A = atria.
In population-based series, agenesis of the corpus callosum occurs in 1 in 4000 to 5000 pregnancies (Ballardini, 2018; Stoll, 2019; Szabo, 2011).
It is associated with other anomalies, aneuploidy, and more than 200 genetic syndromes.
Thus, chromosomal microarray analysis should be offered, and genetic counseling can be challenging.
In a review of apparently isolated cases, fetal MR imaging identified additional brain abnormalities in more than 20 percent of cases .
If MR imaging does not identify associated abnormalities, normal developmental outcome in 67 to 75 percent of cases and severe disability in about 10 percent has been reported (des Portes, 2018; Sotiriadis, 2012).
# Holoprosencephaly.
During early normal brain development, the prosencephalon or forebrain divides as it becomes the telencephalon and diencephalon.
With holoprosencephaly, the prosencephalon fails to divide completely into two separate cerebral hemispheres and underlying paired diencephalic structures.
The most severe form, alobar holoprosencephaly, is characterized by a single monoventricle that surrounds fused thalami .
In semilobar holoprosencephaly, hemispheres partially separate.
Lobar holoprosencephaly refers to a variable degree of fusion of frontal structures and is more challenging to detect with prenatal ultrasound.
The lobar form is among possible diagnoses when a normal cavum septum pellucidum cannot be visualized.
Last, the middle interhemispheric variant of holoprosencephaly is characterized by communication between the midportion of the bodies of the lateral ventricles with separation of the frontal horns, such that the choroid plexus may prolapse from one lateral ventricle into the other.
Differentiation into two cerebral hemispheres is induced by prechordal mesenchyme, which is also responsible for differentiation of the midline face.
Craniofacial anomalies associated with holoprosencephaly are reviewed later (p. 283).
Figure 15-13.
Alobar holoprosencephaly.
The thalami (Th) are fused and encircled by a monoventricle (V) with a covering mantle (M) of cortex.
The midline falx is absent.
Reproduced with permission from Rafael Levy, RDMS.
The birth prevalence of holoprosencephaly is only 1 in 10,000.
However, the abnormality has been identified in nearly 1 in 250 early abortuses, which attests to extremely high in-utero lethality (Orioli, 2010; Yamada, 2004).
The alobar form accounts for 40 to 75 percent of cases, and 30 to 40 percent have a numerical chromosomal abnormality, particularly trisomy 13 (Orioli, 2010; Solomon, 2010).
Conversely, of trisomy 13 cases, two thirds are found to have holoprosencephaly.
# Dandy-Walker Malformation.
This posterior fossa abnormality is characterized by agenesis of the cerebellar vermis, posterior fossa enlargement, and elevation of the tentorium cerebelli.
The cerebellar hemispheres are visibly separated, and fluid in the cisterna magna communicates with the fourth ventricle through the cerebellar vermis defect .
The birth prevalence approximates 1 in 12,000 .
Associated anomalies and aneuploidy are common.
These include ventriculomegaly in 30 to 40 percent, other anomalies in approximately 50 percent, and aneuploidy in 40 percent (Ecker, 2000; Long, 2006).
Dandy-Walker malformation is also associated with numerous genetic and sporadic syndromes, congenital viral infections, and teratogen exposure, all of which greatly affect the prognosis.
Thus, the initial evaluation mirrors that for ventriculomegaly (p. 278).
Figure 15-14.
Dandy-Walker malformation.
A. The cerebellar hemispheres (CH) are widely separated by a fluid collection that connects the 4th ventricle (4V) to the enlarged cisterna magna (CM).
B. Sagittal image depicts elevation of the tentorium (arrows).
Inferior vermian agenesis is a term used when only the inferior portion of the vermis is absent.
Even with partial and relatively subtle vermian agenesis, the prevalence of associated anomalies and aneuploidy is still high, and the prognosis is often poor (Ecker, 2000; Long, 2006).
# Schizencephaly and Porencephaly.
Schizencephaly is a rare brain abnormality characterized by clefts in one or both cerebral hemispheres, typically involving the perisylvian fissure.
The cleft is lined by heterotopic gray matter and communicates with the ventricle, extending through the cortex to the pial surface .
Schizencephaly is believed to be an abnormality of neuronal migration, which explains its typically delayed recognition until after midpregnancy .
It is associated with absence of the cavum septum pellucidum, resulting in frontal horn communication.
Ventriculomegaly is a common finding.
Figure 15-15.
Schizencephaly.
This transverse image shows a large cleft extending from the right lateral ventricle through the cortex.
Because the borders of the cleft are separate, the defect is termed open-lipped.
Reproduced with permission from Michael Davidson, RDMS.
In contrast, porencephaly is a cystic space within the brain that is lined by white matter and may or may not communicate with the ventricular system.
It is generally considered to be a destructive lesion.
Porencephaly may develop following intracranial hemorrhage in the setting of neonatal alloimmune thrombocytopenia or in an individual with a COL4A-1 mutation —a genetic condition which causes familial porencephaly.
In a monochorionic twin gestation, acute hypotension following death of a cotwin also may create porencephaly.
Fetal MR imaging should be considered when either of these CNS anomalies is identified.
# Microcephaly.
This condition indicates that the size of the head is profoundly smaller than expected.
The Society for Maternal-Fetal Medicine (2016) recommends that fetal microcephaly be defined as a head circumference at least 3 standard deviations (SD) below the mean for gestational age (Appendix, p. 1237).
However, many fetuses with measurements in this range have normal head size at birth, and therefore the diagnosis of pathologic microcephaly is not considered certain until the head circumference reaches 5 SD below the mean .
The forehead is often upsloping.
Microcephaly is associated with a wide range of underlying abnormalities, genetic syndromes, and congenital infections such as toxoplasmosis, rubella, and cytomegalovirus, herpes, or Zika infection .
Findings that suggest infection include parenchymal and periventricular echogenic foci, ventriculomegaly, and cerebellar hypoplasia.
Amniocentesis should be offered, and fetal MR imaging should be considered.
The Society for Maternal-Fetal Medicine (2016) recommends performing a detailed ultrasound examination of the fetal brain if the head circumference measures more than 2 SD below the mean.
Another ultrasound evaluation follows in 3 or 4 weeks, with the understanding that it may be difficult to distinguish constitutionally small head size from pathologic findings.
# Sacrococcygeal Teratoma.
This germ cell tumor is one of the most common tumors in neonates, with a birth prevalence of approximately 1 in 28,000 (Derikx, 2006; Swamy, 2008).
It is thought to arise from the totipotent cells along the Hensen node, anterior to the coccyx.
Sacrococcygeal teratoma (SCT) classification includes four types .
Type 1 is predominantly external with a minimal presacral component; type 2 is predominantly external but with a significant intrapelvic component; type 3 is predominantly internal and has abdominal extension; and type 4 is entirely internal with no external component.
The tumor histological type may be mature, immature, or malignant.
Sonographically, SCT is a solid and/or cystic mass that arises from the anterior sacrum and usually extends inferiorly and externally as it grows .
Solid components often vary in echogenicity, appear disorganized, and may enlarge rapidly with advancing gestation.
Fetal MR imaging should
be considered because internal pelvic components may be challenging to visualize.
Large, solid tumors frequently result in hydrops due to high-output cardiac failure, either as a consequence of tumor vascularity or secondary to bleeding within the tumor and resultant anemia.
Hydramnios is common.
Fetuses with tumors >5 cm often require cesarean delivery, and classical hysterotomy may be needed .
Fetal therapy for SCT is discussed in Chapter 19 (p. 373).
Figure 15-16.
Sacrococcygeal teratoma.
This tumor enlarged from 3 cm in diameter at 19 weeks’ gestation (A) to 9 cm in diameter during a 5-week period (B).
Arrows depict the external borders of the mass.
# Caudal Regression Sequence.
This rare anomaly is characterized by absence of the sacral spine and often portions of the lumbar spine.
It is approximately 25 times more prevalent in pregnancies complicated by diabetes .
Caudal regression is associated with genitourinary malformations and syndromes such as the VACTERL association (vertebral defects, anal atresia, cardiac defects, tracheo-esophageal fistula, renal anomalies, and limb abnormalities) .
Sonographic findings include a spine that appears abnormally short, lacks normal lumbosacral curvature, and terminates abruptly above the level of the iliac wings .
Because the sacrum does not lie between the iliac wings, they are abnormally close together and may appear shield-like.
The lower extremities lack normal soft tissue development and may be abnormally positioned.
Figure 15-17.
Caudal regression sequence.
A. The spine is markedly foreshortened.
The arrow shows where it terminates.
B. The spine ends abruptly above the level of the iliac wings (I).
C. Without a vertebral body between the iliac wings (I), they assume a shield shape.
# Sirenomelia.
This rare anomaly may be confused with caudal regression sequence but is quite different.
Formerly termed mermaid syndrome, it is characterized by a single lower extremity in the midline and bilateral renal agenesis.
The extremity may contain one or two sets of bones and feet .
The bladder, anus, and genitalia are absent.
What may appear to be a single umbilical artery in these cases is instead a remnant of the vitelline artery.
After 18 weeks’ gestation, when the kidneys become the primary source of amnionic fluid production, resultant anhydramnios may complicate the diagnosis.
Cases of surviving infants have a variant of sirenomelia in which there is some functioning renal tissue and urinary output .
Figure 15-18.
Sirenomelia.
A. This single lower extremity contained two femur bones (F), two lower leg bones (LL), and a fused foot with toes pointing outward ().
B. Arrows show the soft tissue outline of the lower extremity.
Amnionic fluid is visible only because the gestational age is 17 weeks’ gestation.
By 18 weeks, absence of kidneys and bladder resulted in anhydramnios.
Reproduced with permission from Melissa Salvie, RDMS.
# Hemivertebrae.
These spinal segmentation-fusion defects are characterized by abnormal development of half of the vertebral body.
Affected vertebrae are triangular and may be separate or fused to adjacent vertebral bodies.
This leads to abnormal curvature of the spine such as scoliosis .
Prenatally diagnosed cases typically involve the thoraco–lumbar spine.
Associated abnormalities are common, particularly skeletal, renal, and cardiac defects (Basude, 2015; Yulia, 2020).
Hemivertebrae are also a component of several syndromes, including the VACTERL association.
Figure 15-19.
Hemivertebrae result in abnormal spinal curvature in these coronal images.
Reproduced with permission from Rose Muli, RDMS.
Head, Face, And Neck.
Craniofacial anatomy on the detailed anatomic survey may include cranial integrity and shape of the skull (Fig. 15-2A); images of the orbits, nose, and lips; views of the maxilla, mandible, hard palate, and tongue; images of the ears; and evaluation of the neck .
Of these structures, only the upper lip is a component of the standard examination.
At Parkland Hospital, we include an image of the sagittal profile as part of
our standard examination to help detect micrognathia prenatally.
Figure 15-20.
Normal craniofacial and neck anatomy.
A. Transverse images of orbits (O) and nose (N).
The small circle within each orbit is the lens.
The distance between the orbits roughly approximates the width of each orbit.
B. Sagittal view of the face, depicting the nasal bone (NB), lips (L), maxilla (Max), and mandible (Man).
C. Transverse image of the alveolar ridge.
D. Coronal view of the nose, upper lip, and lower lip.
E. Sagittal image of the neck.
F. Image of the ear.
Reproduced with permission from Devi Nanandhan, RDMS.
When imaging the neck, particularly in the third trimester, identifying a nuchal cord is not uncommon .
This finding is not associated with adverse outcome, and we do not alter fetal surveillance if a nuchal cord is detected.
Figure 15-21.
Nuchal cord incidentally noted with color Doppler in a transverse image of the fetal neck at 34 weeks’ gestation.
# Dolichocephaly and Brachycephaly.
The cephalic index reflects the skull shape.
It is measured by dividing the biparietal diameter by the occipitofrontal diameter.
The cephalic index is normally 70 to 86 percent.
It is smaller if the head shape is flattened— dolichocephaly, and larger if the shape is rounded—brachycephaly.
In such cases, the head circumference measurement more reliably estimates gestational age than does the biparietal diameter .
These head shape variants may be normal or can be secondary to fetal position or oligohydramnios.
Dolichocephaly can occur with neural-tube defects, and brachycephaly may be seen in fetuses with Down syndrome.
A strawberryshaped skull describes a pattern of angulation typical of trisomy 18 (Fig. 165, p. 312).
With any abnormal skull shape, craniosynostosis is a consideration.
Figure 15-22.
Transthalamic images demonstrating dolichocephaly (A) and brachycephaly (B).
The biparietal diameter (BPD) and head circumference (HC) are measured in each image.
# Abnormalities of Orbits and Nose.
Subjectively, the distance in between the orbits is similar to the diameter of each orbit (see Fig. 15-20).
The lens is often visible.
Nomograms are available for the ocular diameter and for the interorbital and binocular distances (Appendix, p. 1240).
Hypertelorism is a common finding in trisomy 18.
Hypotelorism, with or without microphthalmia, may be found in the setting of holoprosencephaly.
In its extreme form only a single orbit is visible—cyclopia.
Other comorbid anomalies with holoprosencephaly include a single nostril—cebocephaly, or absence of the entire nose (arhinia) with proboscis .
Figure 15-23.
Abnormalities of the orbits.
A. Hypertelorism in a fetus with trisomy 18.
B. Hypotelorism in a fetus with trisomy 13 and alobar holoprosencephaly.
C. Microphthalmia.
This fetus also had trisomy 13.
Arrows point to the eyes.
Figure 15-24.
Nasal abnormalities associated with holoprosencephaly.
A. Sagittal profile depicting a proboscis (arrow) protruding from the forehead.
B. Coronal image demonstrating the proboscis along with hypotelorism and absence of the nose.
C. Coronal image demonstrating a single nostril (cebocephaly).
D. Photograph of a newborn with cebocephaly.
Nasal bone hypoplasia or sonographic absence is an aneuploidy marker that confers increased risk for fetal Down syndrome .
It is not a structural abnormality.
Nasal bone measurement is part of the detailed ultrasound examination and is measured only between 15 and 22 weeks’ gestation.
The measurement is considered foreshortened if less than 2.5 mm or if more than 2 SD below the mean for gestational age .
Hypoplasia of the nose is a different condition that can occur following warfarin exposure (Fig. 8-4, p. 156).
Figure 15-25.
Nasal bone (and its absence).
A. Sagittal image of the profile showing measurement of a normal nasal bone at 19 weeks.
B. Fetus with trisomy 21, also at 19 weeks, with no visible nasal bone.
Reproduced with permission from Jason McWhirt, RDMS.
# Facial Clefts.
These are grouped into three main types.
The first type, cleft lip and palate, always
involves the lip, may also involve the hard palate, can be unilateral or bilateral, and has a birth prevalence that approximates 1 in 1000 (Cragan, 2009; Dolk, 2010).
If isolated, the inheritance is multifactorial—with a recurrence risk of 3 to 5 percent for one prior affected child.
If a cleft is visible in the upper lip, a transverse image at the level of the alveolar ridge may demonstrate that the defect also involves the primary palate .
Figure 15-26.
Cleft lip/palate.
A. This fetus has a prominent unilateral (left-sided) cleft lip.
B. Transverse view of the palate in the same fetus demonstrates a defect in the alveolar ridge (arrow).
The tongue (T) is also visible.
In one review of low-risk pregnancies, cleft lip was identified sonographically in only about half of cases .
Approximately 40 percent of those detected prenatally are associated with other anomalies or syndromes, and aneuploidy is common (Maarse, 2011; Offerdal, 2008).
The rate of associated anomalies is highest for bilateral defects that involve the palate.
In the Utah Birth Defect Network, aneuploidy was identified in 1 percent with cleft lip alone, 5 percent with unilateral cleft lip and palate, and 13 percent with bilateral cleft lip and palate .
The second type of cleft is isolated cleft palate.
It begins at the uvula, may involve the soft palate, and occasionally involves the hard palate—but does not involve the lip.
The birth prevalence approximates 1 in 2000 .
Identification of an isolated cleft palate has been described using detailed sonography, and particularly with three-dimensional imaging, but detection is not feasible in all cases (Ramos, 2010; Wilhelm, 2010).
Isolated cleft palate is not expected to be visualized during a standard ultrasound examination (Maarse, 2011; Offerdal, 2008).
A third type of cleft is median cleft lip, which may be found in fetuses with holoprosencephaly, typically when hypotelorism is also present.
Additionally, a median cleft may be associated with hypertelorism and frontonasal dysplasia, formerly called the median cleft face syndrome.
# Micrognathia.
The fetal profile can help identify cases of micrognathia—hypoplasia of the mandible, and retrognathia, which is recession of the mandible in relation to the maxilla .
To quantify micrognathia risk, a transverse image of the mandible can be used to calculate the jaw index, which is the anteriorposterior diameter of the mandible expressed as a percentage of the biparietal diameter .
Fetuses with micrognathia and retrognathia frequently have a posterior cleft palate and glossoptosis (recessed tongue)—a constellation of findings known as the Pierre Robin sequence.
Micrognathia is also a feature of Treacher Collins syndrome, oralfacial-digital syndromes, trisomies 18 and 13, triploidy, and the 22 q11.2 deletion.
Micrognathia may result in hydramnios and can cause airway obstruction at birth.
Use of the ex-utero intrapartum treatment (EXIT) procedure for severe micrognathia is discussed in Chapter 19 (p. 379).
Figure 15-27.
Micrognathia.
A. Sagittal image of a fetus with severe micrognathia.
B. 3-dimensional ultrasound rendering depicts the recessed chin and downslanting palpebral fissures.
C. A transverse image of the mandible was used to calculate a jaw index for this fetus.
Micrognathia should not be confused with agnathia–otocephaly, a rare anomaly in which no mandible develops and the ears may fuse in the midline .
The latter confers an extremely poor prognosis and has been diagnosed as early as the late first trimester .
Figure 15-28.
Agnathia-otocephaly, ultrasound (A) and postdelivery (B) images.
With this rare, lethal anomaly the mandible fails to develop, and the ears are inferiorly displaced and may be fused in the midline.
# Epignathus.
This rare teratoma arises from the oral cavity or pharynx.
It may grow outward or both outward and into the brain, the latter conferring an extremely poor prognosis .
If brain involvement is absent, an EXIT procedure, reviewed in Chapter 19 (p. 379), can help secure the airway at delivery .
Figure 15-29.
Epignathus, ultrasound (A) and postdelivery (B) images.
This teratoma arises from the oral cavity or pharynx and may grow outward from the mouth or both outward and into the brain, as in this fetus (arrowhead).
Arrows depict the external extent of the mass.
Reproduced with permission from Halima Abdirahman, RDMS.
# Cystic Hygroma.
This venolymphatic malformation is characterized by fluid-filled sacs that extend from the posterior neck .
Cystic hygromas may be diagnosed in the first trimester and vary widely in size.
Impaired lymphatic drainage from the head into the jugular vein leads to an accumulation of fluid in jugular lymphatic sacs.
The birth prevalence of cystic hygromas approximates 1 in 5000.
However, reflecting the high in-utero lethality of the condition, the first-trimester incidence exceeds 1 in 300 .
Figure 15-30.
Cystic hygromas.
A. This 9-week fetus with a cystic hygroma (arrow) was later found to have Noonan syndrome.
B. Massive multiseptated hygromas (arrowheads) in the setting of hydrops fetalis at 15 weeks’ gestation.
Up to 70 percent of cystic hygromas are associated with aneuploidy.
When cystic hygromas are diagnosed in the first trimester, trisomy 21 is the most common aneuploidy, followed by 45,X and trisomy 18 (Kharrat, 2006; Malone, 2005).
First-trimester fetuses with cystic hygromas are five times more likely to be aneuploid than fetuses with a thickened nuchal translucency.
When cystic hygromas are diagnosed in the second trimester, approximately 75 percent of aneuploid cases are 45,X—Turner syndrome (Johnson, 1993; Shulman, 1992).
Even in the absence of aneuploidy, cystic hygromas confer a significantly greater risk for other abnormalities, particularly flow-related cardiac defects.
These include hypoplastic left heart and coarctation of the aorta (p. 292).
Cystic hygromas may also be part of a genetic syndrome such as Noonan syndrome, an autosomal dominant disorder that shares several features with 45,X. Noonan syndrome is characterized by short stature, lymphedema, high-arched palate, and often pulmonary valve stenosis.
Large cystic hygromas are usually associated with hydrops fetalis, rarely resolve, and carry a poor prognosis.
Small hygromas may undergo spontaneous resolution, and provided that fetal karyotype and echocardiography results are normal, the prognosis may be good.
The likelihood of a nonanomalous liveborn neonate with normal karyotype following identification of first-trimester hygroma approximates 1 in 6 (Kharrat, 2006; Malone, 2005).
Thorax.
Thoracic anatomy imaged in the detailed anatomic survey may include the lungs, ribs, and diaphragm.
The lungs should appear homogeneous and symmetric, each occupying approximately one third of the area in the fourchamber view of the heart .
The thoracic circumference is measured at the skin line in a transverse plane at the level of the fourchamber view.
If pulmonary hypoplasia is suspected secondary to a small thorax, such as with a severe skeletal dysplasia, comparison with a reference table may be helpful (Appendix, p. 1238).
Representative images of the diaphragm are usually obtained in the parasagittal or coronal plane.
The diaphragm appears as a hypoechoic line between the lungs and liver.
Thoracic abnormalities may appear sonographically as cystic or solid spaceoccupying lesions or as an effusion outlining the heart or lung(s).
Fetal therapy for thoracic abnormalities is discussed in Chapter 19 (p. 376).
Figure 15-31.
Normal thoracic anatomy.
A. The lungs each occupy one third of the area in the fourchamber view of the heart.
B. The diaphragm (arrow) appears as a hypoechoic line in between the lung and liver in this parasagittal view.
LA = left atrium; LV = left ventricle; RA = right atrium; RV = right ventricle.
# Diaphragmatic Hernia.
This is a defect in the diaphragm through which abdominal organs herniate into the thorax.
It is left-sided in approximately 75 percent of cases, rightsided in 20 percent, and bilateral in 5 percent .
The prevalence of congenital diaphragmatic hernia (CDH) is 1 in 3000 to 5000 births
Cragan, 2009; Dolk, 2010).
Associated anomalies and aneuploidy are found in 40 percent of cases (Gallot, 2007; Stege, 2003).
In population-based series, an associated abnormality reduces the overall survival rate of neonates with CDH from approximately 50 percent to about 20 percent (Colvin, 2005; Gallot, 2007).
Without other abnormalities, the major causes of neonatal mortality are pulmonary hypoplasia and pulmonary hypertension.
Left-sided CDH typically causes dextroposition of the heart to the right side of the thorax, such that the cardiac axis points toward the midline .
Accompanying findings include the stomach bubble or bowel peristalsis in the chest and a wedge-shaped mass—the liver—located anteriorly in the left hemithorax.
Liver herniation complicates at least 50 percent of cases and is associated with a 30-percent reduction in the survival rate .
With large lesions, impaired swallowing and mediastinal shift may result in hydramnios and hydrops, respectively.
Figure 15-32.
Congenital diaphragmatic hernia.
In this transverse view of the thorax, the heart is shifted to the right side of the chest by a left-sided diaphragmatic hernia containing stomach (S), liver (L), and bowel (B).
An effort to reduce neonatal mortality rates and need for extracorporeal membrane oxygenation (ECMO) has focused on prognostic indicators such as the sonographic lung-to-head ratio, described in Chapter 19 (p. 375).
MR imaging parameters include measurements of lung volume and degree of liver herniation (Dutemeyer, 2020; Oluyomi-Obi, 2017; Worley, 2009).
# Congenital Cystic Adenomatoid Malformation.
This abnormality represents a hamartomatous overgrowth of terminal bronchioles that communicates with the tracheobronchial tree.
It is also called congenital pulmonary airway malformation (CPAM), based on an understanding that not all histopathological types are cystic or adenomatoid (Azizkhan, 2008; Stocker, 1977 2002).
The estimated prevalence is 1 in 6000 to 8000 births, and this rate is rising because of improved sonographic detection of milder cases (Burge, 2010; Duncombe, 2002; Lau, 2017).
With ultrasound, a congenital cystic adenomatoid malformation (CCAM) is as a well-circumscribed mass that may appear solid and echogenic or may have one or multiple variably sized cysts .
It usually involves one lobe, receives its blood supply from the pulmonary artery, and has pulmonary venous drainage.
Lesions with cysts ≥5 mm are generally termed macrocystic, and lesions that appear solid or have cysts <5 mm are microcystic .
Figure 15-33.
Congenital cystic adenomatoid malformation (CCAM).
A. This left-sided microcystic CCAM is an echogenic mass that fills the left hemithorax and causes mediastinal shift, which displaces the heart (arrows) to the right side of the chest.
B. This left-sided macrocystic CCAM contains a cyst as large as the heart and also displaces the heart to the right.
C. This right-sided CCAM contains multiple cysts of varying size () and displaces the heart farther to the left side of the chest (arrows).
In a review of 645 CCAM cases, the neonatal survival rate exceeded 95 percent, and 30 percent of cases demonstrated apparent prenatal resolution.
The other 5 percent of cases—typically very large lesions with associated mediastinal shift—were complicated by hydrops and had poor prognosis .
Microcystic CCAMs usually become less conspicuous with advancing gestation, because in addition to occupying less of the thorax, their echogenicity more closely resembles surrounding lung tissue.
However, a subset of CCAMs may demonstrate rapid growth between 18 and 26 weeks’ gestation.
Corticosteroid therapy has been used for large microcystic lesions to forestall growth and potentially ameliorate hydrops (Curran, 2010; Peranteau, 2016).
If a large dominant cyst is present, thoracoamnionic shunt placement may lead to hydrops resolution.
Fetal therapy for CCAM is discussed in Chapter 19 (p. 370).
# Pulmonary Sequestration.
Also called a bronchopulmonary sequestration, this abnormality is an accessory lung bud
sequestered” from the tracheobronchial tree.
It is nonfunctioning lung tissue.
Most cases diagnosed prenatally are extralobar, which means they are enveloped in their own pleura.
Overall, however, most sequestrations present in adulthood and are intralobar—within the pleura of another lobe.
Extralobar pulmonary sequestration is considered significantly less common than CCAM, and no precise prevalence has been reported.
Lesions have a left-sided predominance and most often involve the left lower lobe.
Associated anomalies have been reported in approximately 10 percent of cases .
Sonographically, pulmonary sequestration presents as a homogeneous, echogenic thoracic mass (Fig. 15-34A).
Thus, it may resemble a microcystic CCAM.
However, the blood supply is from the systemic circulation—from the aorta—rather than the pulmonary artery (Fig. 15-34B).
Approximately 10 to 20 percent are located below the diaphragm.
A small percentage of fetuses with pulmonary sequestration develop a large ipsilateral pleural effusion, and without treatment, this may result in pulmonary hypoplasia or hydrops (Fig. 15-34C).
Treatment with thoracoamnionic shunting is discussed in Chapter 19 (p. 376).
Hydrops may also result from mediastinal shift or highoutput cardiac failure due to the left-to-right shunt imposed by the mass.
In the absence of a pleural effusion, the reported survival rate exceeds 95 percent, and 40 percent of cases demonstrate apparent prenatal resolution .
Figure 15-34.
Pulmonary sequestration.
A. Transverse image of the thorax depicts a left lower lobe pulmonary sequestration (PS) in this 25-week fetus.
B. Sagittal image showing that blood supply to the mass is from a branch of the abdominal aorta, which confirms the diagnosis.
C. Over the next 3 weeks, a large ipsilateral pleural effusion develops (asterisk), resulting in mediastinal shift and dextroposition of the heart to the far-right thorax.
D. After placement of a double-pigtail shunt through the chest wall, which drains the effusion into the amnionic fluid, the lung significantly reexpanded.
Arrows point to coils of the pigtail shunt.
Reproduced with permission from Dr. Elaine Duryea.
# Congenital High Airway Obstruction Sequence.
This rare anomaly usually results from laryngeal or tracheal atresia.
The normal egress of lung fluid is obstructed, and the tracheobronchial tree and lungs become massively distended.
Sonographically, the lungs are brightly echogenic, the bronchi are dilated, the diaphragm is flattened or everted, and the heart is compressed .
Impaired venous return leads to development of ascites, typically followed by hydrops.
In one review of 118 cases, associated anomalies were identified in more than 50 percent .
Congenital high airway obstruction sequence (CHAOS) is a feature of the autosomal recessive Fraser syndrome and has been associated with the 22q11.2 deletion syndrome.
In some cases, the obstructed airway spontaneously perforates, which potentially confers a better prognosis.
The EXIT procedure has significantly improved outcome in selected cases.
Figure 15-35.
Congenital high airway obstruction sequence (CHAOS).
The lungs (L) appear brightly echogenic, and the bronchi (arrow) are dilated with fluid.
Flattening and eversion of the diaphragm is common, as is ascites (asterisks).
Heart.
Cardiac malformations are the most common class of congenital anomalies.
Their overall prevalence is 8 cases in 1000 births .
Almost 90 percent of cardiac defects are multifactorial or polygenic in origin, another 1 to 2 percent result from a single-gene disorder or gene-deletion syndrome, and 1 to 2 percent may occur from exposure to a teratogen such as maternal diabetes or isotretinoin.
Based on data from population-based registries, approximately 1 in 8 liveborn and stillborn neonates with a congenital heart defect has a chromosomal abnormality (Dolk, 2010; Hartman, 2011).
Trisomy 21 accounts for most of these cases, followed by trisomy 18, 22q11.2 deletion, trisomy 13, and monosomy X .
Approximately 50 to 70 percent of aneuploid fetuses with
cardiac anomalies are also found to have noncardiac abnormalities.
Traditionally, congenital cardiac anomalies have been more challenging to detect than anomalies of other organ systems.
Recent series suggest that standard ultrasound may identify 50 to 60 percent of those with major cardiac anomalies before 22 weeks’ gestation (Byrne, 2020; Sun, 2018).
Prenatal detection may improve neonatal survival, particularly for ductaldependent lesions, that is, those requiring prostaglandin infusion after birth to keep the ductus arteriosus open (Franklin, 2002; Mahle, 2001; Tworetzky, 2001).
# Standard Cardiac Examination.
Standard cardiac assessment includes a four-chamber view, evaluation of rate and rhythm, evaluation of the left and right ventricular outflow tracts, and when feasible, documentation of the 3-vessel view and 3-vessel trachea view (Figs. 15-36 and 15-37).
It is hoped that examination of the cardiac outflow tracts and 3-vessel views will improve detection of outflow tract abnormalities that may have a normal-appearing four-chamber view, such as tetralogy of Fallot and transposition of the great arteries.
Centers with expertise have reported at least 90 percent detection of such anomalies with incorporation of these views (Brandt, 2015; Palatnik, 2016).
Figure 15-36.
Diagram showing measurement of cardiac axis from the four-chamber view.
LA = left atrium; LV = left ventricle; RA = right atrium; RV = right ventricle.
Figure 15-37.
Standard and detailed examination cardiac views.
A. Four-chamber view.
B. Left ventricular outflow tract view.
Arrow depicts mitral valve becoming the posterior wall of the aorta.
The arrow with asterisk marks the interventricular septum becoming the anterior aortic wall.
C. Right ventricular outflow tract view.
D. Three-vessel view.
E. Three-vessel trachea view F. High short-axis view (outflow tracts).
G. Aortic arch view.
H. Ductal arch view.
I. Superior and inferior vena cavae views.
AA = aortic arch; Ao = aorta; DA = ductal arch; IVC = inferior vena cava; LA = left atrium; LV = left ventricle; PA = pulmonary artery; RA = right atrium; RV = right ventricle; SVC = superior vena cava; T = trachea.
The four-chamber view is a transverse image of the fetal thorax at a level immediately above the diaphragm.
It allows evaluation of cardiac size, position in the thorax, cardiac axis, atria and ventricles, foramen ovale, atrial septum primum, interventricular septum, and atrioventricular valves (Fig. 1537A).
The left ventricle is apex-forming, and two pulmonary veins are often visible entering the left atrium.
The atria and ventricles should be similar in size, and the apex of the heart should form a 45-degree angle with the left anterior chest wall (see Fig. 15-36).
Abnormalities of cardiac axis are encountered in more than one third of fetuses with structural cardiac anomalies (Shipp, 1995; Crane, 1997; Sinkovskaya, 2015).
The left ventricular outflow tract view demonstrates that the ascending aorta arises entirely from the left ventricle.
The interventricular septum is shown to be in continuity with the anterior wall of the aorta, and the mitral valve in continuity with the posterior wall of the aorta (Fig. 15-37B).
Ventricular septal defects and outflow tract abnormalities are often visible in this view.
The right ventricular outflow tract view shows the right ventricle giving rise to the main pulmonary artery, which subsequently branches into the right and left pulmonary arteries.
Fig. 15-37C,F).
Together, the left and right outflow tract views demonstrate the normal perpendicular orientation of the aorta and pulmonary artery and the comparable size of these great arteries.
The 3-vessel view (3VV) is a transverse image obtained just above the base of the heart.
The three vessels line up in a row: an oblique view of the pulmonary artery, which should appear long and cylindrical; a crosssectional image of the ascending aorta; and a cross-sectional image of the superior vena cava (SVC) (Fig. 15-37D).
The pulmonary artery and aorta should be similar in diameter.
The 3-vessel trachea view
3VTV) also is a transverse image but is obtained further cephalad.
It includes the pulmonary artery giving rise to the ductus arteriosus as it makes a V-shape with the aortic arch, along with the SVC and the trachea (Fig. 15-37E).
The 3VTV can be helpful for identifying aortic arch abnormalities, particularly ductaldependent lesions.
# Specialized Cardiac Examination.
The detailed ultrasound examination includes the five cardiac components of the standard examination plus the superior and inferior vena cavae and the aortic and ductal arch views (Fig. 15-37G–I).
The examination also involves evaluation of the interventricular septum and cardiac situs, documentation of which may be facilitated with video clips.
Fetal echocardiography is a more extensive examination of cardiac structure and function designed to characterize abnormalities.
In addition to grayscale imaging views, echocardiography includes evaluation of cardiac rate and rhythm, color Doppler ultrasound, pulsed-wave Doppler ultrasound, cardiac biometry, and if clinically relevant, cardiac function assessment .
These components are beyond the scope of this text.
Echocardiography indications are discussed in Chapter 14 (p. 252).
Selected cardiac anomalies are reviewed next.
Ventricular Septal Defect This is the most common congenital cardiac anomaly.
It is found in approximately 1 in 300 births (Bjornard, 2013; Cragan, 2009; Dolk, 2010).
A defect may be appreciated in the perimembranous or muscular portion of the interventricular septum in the four-chamber view, and imaging of the left ventricular outflow tract may show discontinuity of the interventricular septum as it becomes the wall of the aorta .
Color Doppler may demonstrate flow across the defect.
Genetic abnormalities are diagnosed with chromosomal microarray analysis in approximately 1 percent of isolated cases but found in at least 15 percent if other structural abnormalities also are present .
More than a third of prenatally diagnosed ventricular septal defects close in utero, and another third close in the first year of life (Cho, 2017; Paladini, 2002; Svirsky, 2019).
Figure 15-39.
Endocardial cushion defect.
A. During ventricular systole, the lateral leaflets of the mitral and tricuspid valves come together in the midline.
But the atrioventricular valve plane is abnormal, a common atrium (A) is observed, and there is a visible defect (arrow) in the interventricular septum.
B. During diastolic filling, opening of the atrioventricular valves more clearly demonstrates the absence of their medial leaflets.
Endocardial Cushion Defect This is also called an atrioventricular (AV) septal defect or AV canal defect.
It has a birth prevalence of approximately 1 in 2500 and is associated with trisomy 21 in more than half of cases (Christensen, 2013; Cragan, 2009; Dolk, 2010).
The endocardial cushions are the crux of the heart, and defects jointly involve the atrial septum primum, interventricular septum, and medial leaflets of the mitral and tricuspid valves .
The majority of defects are balanced–with ventricles comparable in size.
Some are unbalanced however, with one side of the heart significantly smaller than the other.
The endocardial cushion defect is considered partial if there is absence of the atrial septum primum and a more subtle AV valve plane abnormality, with no ventricular septal defect.
Figure 15-38.
Ventricular septal defect.
A. In this four-chamber view, a defect (arrow) is noted in the perimembranous portion of the interventricular septum.
B. The left ventricular outflow tract view demonstrates a break in continuity (arrow) between the interventricular septum and the anterior wall of the aorta.
Endocardial cushion defects are a common finding in heterotaxy, also known as cardiosplenic or isomerism syndromes.
Heterotaxy implies that thoraco-abdominal organs normally on one side of the body are on an incorrect side, on both sides, or absent, as in polysplenia or asplenia.
Complex cardiac abnormalities are a common feature, particularly endocardial cushion defects.
In a review of 632
pregnancies with fetal heterotaxy, an endocardial cushion defect was present in 60 percent .
These endocardial cushion defects are a particularly at-risk group because of their association with third-degree heart block, which confers a poor prognosis.
Hypoplastic Left Heart Syndrome This anomaly is found in approximately 1 in 4000 births (Bjornard, 2013; Cragan, 2009; Dolk, 2010;).
During second-trimester ultrasound examination, the left ventricle may be so small that a chamber is difficult to appreciate .
Alternately, the left ventricle may be normal in size or dilated but have severely decreased contractility and an echogenic inner wall due to endocardial fibroelastosis.
There may be no visible left ventricular inflow or outflow, and reversal of flow may be documented in the aortic arch in the 3-vessel trachea view.
As gestation advances, the left ventricle and aorta become progressively smaller.
Prenatal detection is nearly 90 percent in population-based registries.
Figure 15-40.
Hypoplastic left heart syndrome.
A. In this four-chamber view, the left ventricle appears “filled in” and echogenic, due to endocardial fibroelastosis.
B. Color Doppler depicts only flow from the right atrium into the right ventricle, and no left ventricular filling is visible.
C. Color Doppler shows reversal of flow in the aortic arch (arrow), which is perfused retrograde via the ductus arteriosus.
LA = left atrium; LV = left ventricle; RA = right atrium; RV = right ventricle.
Hypoplastic left heart syndrome is a ductal-dependent lesion for which neonatal administration of prostaglandin therapy is essential.
Postnatal treatment consists of a three-staged palliative repair—single ventricle palliation, or cardiac transplantation.
Rates of survival to adulthood may reach 70 percent .
However, morbidity is high, and developmental delays are common (Lloyd, 2017; Paladini, 2017; Wilson, 2018).
Fetal therapy for this condition is discussed in Chapter 19 (p. 378).
Coarctation of the Aorta Coarctation refers to narrowing of the aortic arch.
The birth prevalence approximates 1 in 2500 .
Usually, the narrowing is focal and found just distal to the origin of the left subclavian artery at the aortic isthmus.
Alternatively, a long segment of the aorta may be affected.
Coarctation may be isolated or associated with other cardiac anomalies, such as hypoplastic left heart syndrome, unbalanced endocardial cushion defect, or double-outlet right ventricle.
The most common sonographic finding is disproportion in ventricular size, with the left ventricle smaller than the right.
However, only one third with this finding have coarctation (Ghi, 2018; van Nisselrooij, 2018).
Other findings include narrowing of the aortic arch in the 3-vessel trachea view or narrowing of the isthmus in the aortic arch view– which may be challenging to image.
Coarctation is associated with Turner syndrome (45,X), with the 22q11.2 deletion, and with autosomal trisomies.
Ebstein Anomaly This rare anomaly is characterized by apical displacement of the tricuspid valve, such that the septal and posterior valve leaflets of the tricuspid valve attach closer to the cardiac apex .
The birth prevalence is approximately 1 in 20,000 .
Fetuses with Ebstein anomaly develop varying degrees of tricuspid regurgitation.
In severe cases, right atrium becomes markedly dilated, and the fetus may develop cardiomegaly and hydrops.
For many years, there was concern that lithium exposure predisposed to Ebstein anomaly.
However, as discussed in Chapter 8 (p. 154), the absolute attributable risk is likely well below 1 percent.
Figure 15-41.
Ebstein anomaly.
A. In this four-chamber view, the tricuspid valve’s septal leaflet attaches closer to the cardiac apex (arrowhead) than the corresponding mitral valve leaflet (arrow).
B. The color Doppler blue jet reflects tricuspid regurgitation.
LA = left atrium; LV = left ventricle; RA = right atrium; RV = right ventricle.
Tetralogy of Fallot This anomaly occurs in approximately 1 in 3000 births (Cragan, 2009; Dolk, 2010; Nelson, 2016).
It includes a
ventricular septal defect; an overriding aorta; a pulmonary valve or pulmonary artery abnormality, and right ventricular hypertrophy .
The last does not usually manifest before birth.
Due to the location of the ventricular septal defect, the fourchamber view may appear normal.
Figure 15-42.
Tetralogy of Fallot.
A. Left ventricular outflow tract view shows a ventricular septal defect with an overriding aorta.
The arrow points to the aortic valve.
B. Right ventricular outflow tract view demonstrating severe pulmonary artery stenosis.
The arrow points to the pulmonary valve.
C. In this fetus with tetralogy of Fallot with absent pulmonary valve, the pulmonary artery shows marked enlargement.
Ao = aorta; LV = left ventricle; PA = pulmonary artery; RV = right ventricle.
The pulmonary artery abnormality is pulmonary stenosis in 60 percent of cases, pulmonary atresia in slightly more than 25 percent, and absent pulmonary valve in 10 to 15 percent .
Absence of the pulmonary valve leads to marked enlargement of the pulmonary artery and poses a risk for hydrops.
The enlarged pulmonary artery can also compress the trachea and cause tracheomalacia.
Chromosomal abnormalities are identified in approximately one third of fetuses with tetralogy of Fallot.
Of these, 22q11.2 deletions compose 15 to 20 percent, and autosomal trisomies constitute 10 percent .
D-Transposition of the Great Arteries This anomaly is characterized by outflow tracts that arise in parallel from the ventricles.
The right ventricle gives rise to the aorta, and the left ventricle to the pulmonary artery .
Thus, there is ventriculo-arterial discordance.
The birth prevalence approximates 1 in 4000 .
The four-chamber view is often normal.
Prenatal detection approximates 40 percent but is thought to improve with visualization of the outflow tracts .
Additionally, the 3-vessel views may demonstrate only two vessels, because the pulmonary artery is underneath the aorta.
Figure 15-43.
D-transposition of the great arteries.
A. Transverse image with color Doppler depicting the outflow tracts arising in parallel.
B. View of the left ventricle giving rise to the pulmonary artery, which subsequently branches (arrows).
C. Sagittal image of the aorta arising anteriorly from the right ventricle and parallel to the pulmonary artery, which arises posteriorly.
Ao = aorta; LV = left ventricle; PA = pulmonary artery; RV = right ventricle.
D-transposition contrasts with L- or corrected transposition of the great arteries, in which there is atrio-ventricular discordance in addition to ventricular-arterial discordance.
L-transposition is strongly associated with other cardiac anomalies and is much less likely to be diagnosed prenatally as an isolated finding.
Double-outlet Right Ventricle With this anomaly, the majority of blood flow to both the pulmonary artery and the aorta comes from the right ventricle.
Double-outlet right ventricle (DORV) is always associated with a ventricular septal defect.
DORV has a spectrum of presentation.
It is categorized according to the location of the ventricular septal defect and the relative proportion of blood flow from the right ventricle to the outflow tracts.
The outflow tracts are often malposed, arising in parallel.
The birth prevalence approximates 1 in 20,000 .
Truncus Arteriosus This rare anomaly is characterized by a single, large outflow tract exiting the heart—a common arterial trunk—rather than a separate aorta and pulmonary artery.
A prominent ventricular septal defect is usually identified, with an enlarged overriding outflow tract that gives rise to pulmonary arteries as well as head and neck vessels .
The differential diagnosis includes tetralogy of Fallot with pulmonary atresia.
The birth prevalence of truncus arteriosus approximates 1 in 16,000 .
In 1949, Collett and Edwards categorized four types of truncus arteriosus according to the origin of the pulmonary arteries.
Characterization of anatomic variants can often only be made postnatally.
Figure 15-44.
Truncus arteriosus.
Grayscale (A) and color Doppler (B) images depict a
single, large outflow tract.
The common arterial trunk (CAT) overlies a ventricular septal defect (arrowhead) and gives rise to the head and neck vessels and pulmonary arteries.
LV = left ventricle; RV = right ventricle.
Reproduced with permission from Paul Mallamaci, RDMS.
Cardiac Rhabdomyoma This is the most common cardiac tumor.
Approximately 50 percent of cases are associated with tuberous sclerosis, an autosomal dominant disease with multiorgan system manifestations.
Tuberous sclerosis is caused by mutations in the hamartin (TSC1) and tuberin (TSC2) genes.
Sonographically, cardiac rhabdomyomas are well-circumscribed echogenic masses, usually within the ventricles or outflow tracts .
They may be single or multiple, may grow in size during gestation, and may occasionally lead to inflow or outflow obstruction.
In cases without obstruction or large tumor size, the prognosis is relatively good from a cardiac standpoint, because the tumors tend to regress after the neonatal period.
Because extracardiac findings of tuberous sclerosis may not be apparent with prenatal sonography, MR imaging may be considered to evaluate fetal CNS anatomy (p. 266).
Figure 15-45.
Rhabdomyoma.
In this four-chamber view of the heart, a large, echogenic, wellcircumscribed mass (R) fills the right ventricle and abuts the tricuspid valve (arrow).
Despite its size, the mass did not obstruct flow, and the neonate did well.
# M-Mode.
Motion-mode or M-mode imaging is a linear display of cardiac cycle events, with time on the x-axis and motion on the y-axis.
It is often used to measure embryonic or fetal heart rate (Fig. 14-1, p. 248).
If an abnormality of heart rate or rhythm is identified, M-mode imaging permits separate evaluation of atrial and ventricular waveforms.
Thus, it is particularly useful for characterizing arrhythmias and their response to treatment .
M-mode can also be used to assess ventricular function and atrial and ventricular outputs.
Premature Atrial Contractions Also called atrial extrasystoles, these are the most common fetal arrhythmia and a frequent finding.
They represent cardiac conduction system immaturity and often resolve with advancing gestation or in the neonatal period.
Premature atrial contractions (PACs) may be conducted and thus sound like extra beats.
However, they are more commonly blocked, and with handheld Doppler they sound like dropped beats.
As shown in Figure 15-46, the dropped beat may be demonstrated with M-mode evaluation as a compensatory pause that follows the premature contraction.
Figure 15-46.
M-mode.
This image demonstrates normal concordance between atrial (A) and ventricular (V) contractions.
Movement of the tricuspid valve (T) is also shown.
The blue arrow denotes a premature atrial contraction followed by a compensatory pause.
PACs are not associated with major structural cardiac abnormalities.
Older case reports describe an association with maternal caffeine consumption and with hydralazine (Lodeiro, 1989; Oei, 1989).
In approximately 2 percent of cases, affected fetuses are later identified to have supraventricular tachycardia (SVT), which is an arrhythmia that requires urgent treatment .
Accordingly, pregnancies with fetal PACs are often followed with fetal heart rate assessment as often as every 1 to 2 weeks until the ectopy resolves.
Treatment of fetal SVT and other arrhythmias is discussed in Chapter 19 (p. 368).
Abdomen.
Abdominal anatomy visible in the second and third trimester includes the stomach, liver, gallbladder, spleen, adrenal glands, kidneys, renal arteries, small and large bowel, and ventral wall.
The stomach is nearly always identified after 14 weeks’ gestation.
Nonvisualization of the stomach may be secondary to impaired swallowing in the setting of oligohydramnios or to underlying causes such as esophageal atresia, a craniofacial anomaly, or a CNS or musculoskeletal abnormality.
Fetuses with hydrops can also have impaired swallowing.
Both the liver and spleen may be viewed in a transverse image obtained at the level of the stomach and intrahepatic portion of the
umbilical vein—the plane at which the abdominal circumference is measured (see Fig. 15-2B).
Hepatosplenomegaly may occur with congenital infection or with hydrops.
By convention, the liver is measured in the sagittal or coronal plane, from the top of the right hemidiaphragm to the inferior tip of the right lobe .
The spleen is posterior to the stomach in the transverse plane.
The gallbladder may be imaged just inferior to the level at which the abdominal circumference is measured.
It lies to the right of the intrahepatic portion of the umbilical vein and has a conical or teardrop shape (see Fig. 15-47B).
Figure 15-47.
Abdominal organs.
A. The liver is measured from the top of the right hemidiaphragm to the inferior tip of the right lobe in this coronal image.
B. Transverse image of the abdomen just inferior to the level at which the abdominal circumference is measured, depicting the gallbladder (G), stomach (S), spleen (Sp), liver (L), and right adrenal gland (A).
The appearance of fetal bowel changes with maturation.
Increased bowel echogenicity may indicate a small amount of swallowed intraamnionic blood, especially if the maternal serum alpha-fetoprotein level is elevated.
The bowel appears as bright as bone in approximately 0.5 percent of secondtrimester fetuses.
In such cases, the risk for fetal trisomy 21 is increased (Fig. 17-3, p. 340).
Echogenic bowel is also associated with fetal cytomegalovirus infection and with cystic fibrosis, in which echogenicity represents inspissated meconium.
# Gastrointestinal Obstruction.
Bowel atresia is characterized by obstruction and proximal bowel dilation.
In general, the more proximal the obstruction, the more likely it is to lead to hydramnios.
The degree of hydramnios from proximal small-bowel obstruction can be sufficiently severe to result in maternal respiratory compromise or preterm labor and may necessitate amnioreduction .
Esophageal Atresia The birth prevalence of this anomaly approximates 1 in 4000 (Cragan, 2009; Pedersen, 2012).
It may be suspected when there is no visible stomach bubble or when the stomach is contracted.
However, because esophageal atresia is associated with a tracheoesophageal fistula in up to 90 percent of cases, fluid is often able to enter the stomach.
More than 50 percent of those with esophageal atresia have other abnormalities or underlying genetic syndromes.
Multiple malformations are present in 30 percent of cases, and aneuploidy such as trisomy 18 or 21, in 10 percent.
Approximately 10 percent of cases of esophageal atresia is found as part of the VACTERL association .
Duodenal Atresia This anomaly occurs in approximately 1 in 10,000 births (Best, 2012; Dolk, 2010).
It is characterized by the sonographic double-bubble sign, which develops from distention of the stomach and the first part of the duodenum .
This finding may not be obvious before 24 weeks’ gestation.
Demonstrating continuity between the stomach and proximal duodenum confirms that the second “bubble” is the proximal duodenum.
Approximately 30 percent of affected fetuses have an associated chromosomal abnormality or genetic syndrome, particularly trisomy 21.
Of cases without a genetic abnormality, a third have associated anomalies, most commonly cardiac defects and other gastrointestinal abnormalities .
Figure 15-48.
Duodenal atresia.
Transverse image of the double-bubble sign, which represents distension of the stomach (S) and the first part of the duodenum (D).
Continuity between these structures confirms that the second cystic structure is the duodenum.
Jejunoileal Atresia This condition may present with dilated small-bowel loops that fill the abdomen or with meconium peritonitis from bowel perforation .
Associated gastrointestinal abnormalities are identified postnatally in 25 percent of cases, with malrotation in 10 to 15 percent .
Cystic fibrosis also is identified in approximately 10 percent.
Figure 15-49.
Jejunoileal atresia with meconium peritonitis.
A. Sagittal image of the fetal abdomen at 26 weeks’ gestation with severe ascites following bowel
perforation.
Arrows point to the bowel, which is considerably more echogenic than the liver.
B. Transverse image at 30 weeks demonstrates resolution of ascites.
The abdomen is now filled with dilated loops of small bowel.
Focal bright echoes (arrows) represent extraluminal meconium.
A = ascites; L = liver.
In general, jejunal atresia is more strongly associated with bowel dilation and hyperperistalsis, and ileal atresia, with perforation.
Bowel dilatation in jejunal atresia typically does not present until after 24 weeks’ gestation and may be accompanied by hydramnios.
Perforation is frequently associated with ascites, and bright echoes may be visible outside the bowel lumen, outlining the peritoneal cavity.
Over time, the ascites resolves, and the extravasated meconium may form a pseudocyst.
Fetal MR imaging can assist with identifying the level of the defect .
Anal Atresia Also known as imperforate anus, this condition is less readily diagnosed by sonography.
Hydramnios is not a typical feature, and the bowel may not be significantly dilated.
A transverse view through the pelvis may show an enlarged rectum as an anechoic structure between the bladder and the sacrum.
Anal atresia is a feature of the VACTERL association.
# Ventral Wall Defects.
The integrity of the abdominal wall is assessed at the level of the cord insertion during the standard examination .
Ventral wall defects include gastroschisis, omphalocele, and body stalk anomaly.
Figure 15-50.
Normal ventral wall.
Transverse view of the abdomen demonstrating normal umbilical cord insertion and integrity of the anterior abdominal wall.
Gastroschisis This is a full-thickness abdominal wall defect located to the right of the umbilical cord insertion.
Bowel herniates through the defect into the amnionic cavity.
Gastroschisis may be diagnosed as early as the late first trimester .
The prevalence is approximately 1 in 2000 births (Jones, 2016; Nelson, 2015).
Gastroschisis is the one major anomaly more common in fetuses of younger mothers, and the average maternal age is 20 years (Santiago-Muñoz, 2007).
Coexisting bowel abnormalities such as jejunal atresia are found in approximately 15 percent of cases .
Gastroschisis is not associated with aneuploidy, and the survival rate is 90 to 95 percent (Nelson, 2015; Raitio, 2020).
Figure 15-51.
Gastroschisis.
Transverse views of the lower abdomen at 13 weeks’ gestation (A) and 18 weeks (B) depict multiple small bowel loops (B) that have herniated into the amnionic cavity through a defect to the right of the cord insertion (arrow).
Fetal-growth restriction complicates gastroschisis in 15 to 40 percent of cases (Overcash, 2014; Santiago-Muñoz, 2007).
Growth restriction does not appear to confer increased mortality (Nelson, 2015; Overcash, 2014).
However, earlier gestational age at delivery does pose a risk for adverse outcome, and planned delivery at 36 to 37 weeks’ gestation has not been found to benefit the neonate (Al-Kaff, 2016; South, 2013).
Omphalocele The birth prevalence of this anomaly approximates 1 in 3000 to 5000 (Canfield, 2006; Dolk, 2010).
It develops when the lateral ectomesodermal folds fail to meet in the midline.
Abdominal organs herniate into the base of the umbilical cord, covered only by a two-layered sac of amnion and peritoneum .
More than half of cases are associated with other major anomalies or aneuploidy.
Aneuploidy is particularly common with smaller defects .
Omphalocele is also a component of several syndromes, including Beckwith–Wiedemann, cloacal exstrophy, and pentalogy of Cantrell.
Neonatal survival approximates 90 percent for isolated cases and 80 percent in those with other structural abnormalities (Raitio, 2021; Springett, 2014).
Isolated defects containing liver are typically delivered via cesarean to decrease the risk for fetal trauma and bleeding.
Figure 15-52.
Omphalocele.
Transverse view of the abdomen showing a large, round, membranecovered ventral wall defect containing exteriorized liver.
Body Stalk Anomaly Also known as limb-body-wall complex or cyllosoma, this rare,
lethal anomaly is characterized by abnormal body wall formation.
Typically, no abdominal wall is visible, and the abdominal organs extrude into the extraamnionic coelom .
The body and placenta are closely approximated or fused, and the umbilical cord is extremely short.
Acuteangle scoliosis is another feature, and amnionic bands are often identified.
Figure 15-53.
Body-stalk anomaly.
A. This 15-week fetus has no visible abdominal wall.
The thorax is disproportionately small compared with the head, and the small lower torso is deviated to the side.
Arrows point to the large mass of extruded abdominal organs.
B. Acute-angle scoliosis.
Arrows depict the abnormal curvature of the spine.
Reproduced with permission from Deirdre Snelson, RDMS.
# Kidneys and Genitourinary Tract.
The fetal kidneys are visible adjacent to the spine, frequently in the first trimester and routinely by 18 weeks’ gestation .
The length of the kidney approximates 20 mm at 20 weeks and grows about 1.1 mm each week thereafter .
Figure 15-54.
Normal fetal kidneys and bladder.
A. The kidneys are visible adjacent to the spine in this 29-week fetus.
A small amount of urine is often visible within the renal pelvis (arrow).
B. Normal fetal bladder, outlined by the two superior vesical arteries as they become the umbilical arteries.
The fetal bladder is also readily seen in the second trimester as a round, anechoic structure in the anterior midline of the pelvis.
With application of Doppler, the bladder is outlined by the two superior vesical arteries as they become the umbilical arteries of the umbilical cord .
The fetal ureters and urethra are not visible sonographically unless abnormally dilated.
After 18 weeks’ gestation, the kidneys are the major source of amnionic fluid .
Normal amnionic fluid volume in the second half of pregnancy suggests urinary tract patency and at least one functioning kidney.
External genitalia are a component of the detailed examination and are part of the standard examination in multifetal gestations and when medically indicated .
Identification may aid counseling in pregnancies at risk for an X-linked genetic condition.
Examples of normal and ambiguous genitalia are shown in Figure 15-55.
Disorders of sexual development are discussed in Chapter 3 (p. 35).
Figure 15-55.
Normal and ambiguous genitalia.
A. Female labia.
B. Male penis and scrotum.
C. Ambiguous genitalia with a phallus and bifid scrotum.
D. With this condition, color Doppler can assist locating the urethral meatus, which is pinpointed here by the urine stream (blue).
Renal Pelvis Dilatation Present in 1 to 5 percent of fetuses, this finding is also called urinary tract dilatation or hydronephrosis.
In 40 to 90 percent of cases, and particularly when mild, renal pelvis dilatation is transient or physiological and does not represent an underlying abnormality (Ismaili, 2003; Nguyen, 2010).
In approximately one third of cases, a urinary tract abnormality is confirmed in the neonatal period.
Of these, ureteropelvic junction (UPJ) obstruction and vesicoureteral reflux (VUR) are the most frequent.
The fetal renal pelvis diameter is measured anterior-to-posterior in a transverse plane.
Calipers are placed on the inner border of the fluid collection .
Although various thresholds have been defined, the pelvis is typically considered dilated if it exceeds 4 mm in the second trimester or 7 mm at approximately 32 weeks’ gestation (Nguyen, 2014; Reddy, 2014).
The second-trimester threshold is used to identify pregnancies that warrant subsequent third-trimester evaluation.
Figure 15-56.
Renal pelvis dilatation.
A. The anterior-posterior diameter of the renal pelves measured 7 mm in the transverse plane in this 34-week fetus.
B. Sagittal image at 32 weeks depicts renal pelvis dilatation with rounded calyces (arrow) in the setting of ureteropelvic junction obstruction.
The Society for Fetal Urology categorized renal pelvis dilatation based on a metaanalysis of more than 100,000 screened pregnancies (Lee, 2006; Nguyen, 2010).
Provided that the finding is isolated, the degree
of dilation correlates with the likelihood of an underlying abnormality.
Associated calyceal dilation, cortical thinning, or dilation elsewhere along the urinary tract confer increased risk .
Mild pyelectasis in the second trimester is a minor aneuploidy marker associated with a slightly increased risk for trisomy 21, particularly when other findings or risk factors are also present (Fig. 17-3, p.
340).
Table 15-2.
Risk for Postnatal Urinary Abnormality According to Degree of Renal Pelvis Dilation Ureteropelvic Junction Obstruction.
This condition is the most common abnormality associated with renal pelvis dilatation.
The birth prevalence is 1 in 1000 to 2000, and males are affected three times more often than females (Williams, 2007; Woodward, 2002).
Obstruction is generally functional rather than anatomical, and it is bilateral in up to a fourth of cases.
The likelihood of UPJ obstruction ranges from 5 percent with mild renal pelvis dilatation to more than 50 percent with severe dilatation .
Duplicated Renal Collecting System.
In this anatomical anomaly, the upper and lower poles of the kidney—called moieties—are each drained by a separate ureter .
Duplication is found in approximately 1 in 4000 pregnancies, is more common in females, and is bilateral in 15 to 20 percent of cases (James, 1998; Vergani, 1998; Whitten, 2001).
Sonographically, an intervening tissue band separates two distinct renal pelves.
Hydronephrosis or ureteral dilation may develop due to abnormal implantation of one or both ureters within the bladder—a relationship that reflects the anatomical Weigert-Meyer rule.
The upper pole ureter tends to develop obstruction from a ureterocele within the bladder, whereas the lower pole ureter has a shortened intravesical segment that predisposes to VUR (see Fig. 15-57).
Thus, both moieties may become dilated from different etiologies, and both are at risk for loss of function.
Figure 15-57.
Duplicated renal collecting system.
A. Renal pelvis dilatation is visible in both the upper (U) and lower (L) pole moieties, which are separated by an intervening band of renal tissue (arrowhead).
B. A ureterocele (arrowhead) is visible within the bladder.
Color Doppler depicts the superior vesical arteries.
Renal Agenesis The estimated prevalence of bilateral renal agenesis is 1 in 8000 births, whereas that of unilateral renal agenesis is 1 in 1000 births (Cragan, 2009; Dolk, 2010; Sheih, 1989; Wiesel, 2005).
With an absent kidney, color Doppler imaging of the descending aorta demonstrates absence of the ipsilateral renal artery .
In addition, the ipsilateral adrenal gland typically enlarges to fill the renal fossa, termed the lying down adrenal sign .
Figure 15-58.
Renal agenesis.
A. Coronal image of a fetus with bilateral renal agenesis in which color Doppler of the abdominal aorta is used to demonstrate absence of the renal arteries.
B. In this fetus with unilateral renal agenesis, arrowheads point to the adrenal gland (arrowheads) filling the renal fossa, which is the “lying-down” adrenal sign.
If renal agenesis is bilateral, no urine is produced, and the resulting anhydramnios leads to pulmonary hypoplasia, limb contractures, and distinctive facies.
When this combination results from renal agenesis, it is called Potter syndrome, after Dr. Edith Potter, who described it in 1946.
When these abnormalities result from severely decreased amnionic fluid volume from another etiology, such as bilateral multicystic dysplastic kidney or autosomal recessive polycystic kidney disease, it is called Potter sequence.
The prognosis for these abnormalities is extremely poor.
Multicystic Dysplastic Kidney This severe form of renal dysplasia results in a nonfunctioning kidney.
The nephrons and collecting ducts form abnormally, such that primitive ducts are surrounded by fibromuscular tissue, and the ureter is atretic .
Sonographically, the kidney contains numerous, variably sized, smoothwalled cysts that do not communicate with the renal pelvis and are surrounded by echogenic cortex .
Figure 15-59.
Multicystic dysplastic
kidneys.
Coronal view of the fetal abdomen demonstrates enlarged kidneys that are filled with cysts of varying size and contain no visible renal pelvis or normalappearing renal tissue.
Unilateral multicystic dysplastic kidney (MCDK) has a prevalence of 1 in 4000 births.
Contralateral renal abnormalities are present in 30 to 40 percent—most frequently VUR or UPJ obstruction .
Nonrenal anomalies have been reported in 25 percent of cases.
Cystic dysplasia may occur as a component of many genetic syndromes (Lazebnik, 1999; Schreuder, 2009).
If MCDK is isolated and unilateral, the prognosis is generally good.
Bilateral MCDK is found in approximately 1 in 12,000 births.
It is associated with severely decreased amnionic fluid volume starting early in gestation.
This leads to Potter sequence and a poor prognosis.
Polycystic Kidney Disease Of the hereditary polycystic diseases, only the infantile form of autosomal recessive polycystic kidney disease (ARPKD) may be reliably diagnosed prenatally.
ARPKD is a chronic, progressive disease of the kidneys and liver that results in cystic dilation of the renal collecting ducts and in congenital hepatic fibrosis .
The carrier frequency of a disease-causing mutation in the PKHD1 gene approximates 1 in 70, and the birth prevalence is 1 in 20,000 .
The phenotypes of ARPKD range from lethal pulmonary hypoplasia at birth to a presentation in late childhood or even adulthood with predominantly hepatic manifestations.
Sonographically, ARPKD displays abnormally large kidneys that may fill or even distend the fetal abdomen and have a solid, ground-glass texture .
Severe oligohydramnios confers a poor prognosis.
Figure 15-60.
Autosomal recessive polycystic kidney disease (ARPKD).
Transverse (A) and coronal (B) images of a 29-week fetus with marked renal enlargement.
The kidneys measure 7 cm in length and have a ground-glass appearance.
There is anhydramnios.
Autosomal dominant polycystic kidney disease (ADPKD), which is far more common, usually does not manifest until adulthood .
Even so, some fetuses with ADPKD have mild renal enlargement and enhanced renal echogenicity in the setting of normal amnionic fluid volume.
The differential diagnosis for these findings includes several genetic syndromes, aneuploidy, or normal variant.
Bladder Outlet Obstruction Distal obstruction of the urinary tract is more frequent in male fetuses, and the most common etiology is posterior urethral valves.
It may be diagnosed as early as the first trimester in some cases .
The bladder is markedly dilated, with accompanying dilation of the proximal urethra, which is termed the “keyhole” sign.
Oligohydramnios, particularly before midpregnancy, portends pulmonary hypoplasia and poor prognosis.
The kidneys may initially manifest severe hydroureteronephrosis but later develop cystic renal dysplasia or become small and echogenic.
Outcome may be poor even with normal amnionic fluid volume.
Associated anomalies occur in 40 percent of cases, and aneuploidy has been reported in 5 to 8 percent (Hayden, 1988; Hobbins, 1984; Mann, 2010).
Evaluation and potential fetal therapy for bladder outlet obstruction is discussed in Chapter 19 (p. 376).
Figure 15-61.
Bladder outlet obstruction.
A. The bladder (B) is so large that it fills the abdomen in this 13-week fetus.
B. By 18 weeks, the kidneys (K) have become brightly echogenic.
C. The bladder is markedly dilated and thick-walled, with dilation of the proximal urethra, termed the “keyhole” sign (arrow).
Skeleton.
The standard examination includes demonstrating the presence of the arms, legs, hands, and feet .
The detailed examination includes, in addition, the number and position of the digits—fingers and toes .
Figure 15-62.
Normal extremities.
A. Footprint with toes identified.
B. Normal ankle position.
C. Hand with fingers identified.
D. Normal hand and forearm position.
The Nosology and Classification of Genetic Skeletal Disorders includes 461 skeletal anomalies in 42 groups, characterized according to their molecular phenotype, clinical features, or radiographic
findings .
More than 90 percent of skeletal disorders now have a known genetic basis, with pathogenic variants identified in more than 400 genes.
The two types of skeletal dysplasias are osteochondrodysplasias—the generalized abnormal development of bone and/or cartilage, and dysostoses—which are abnormalities of individual bones.
In addition to these malformations, skeletal abnormalities include deformations, as with some cases of clubfoot, and disruptions such as limb-reduction defects.
# Skeletal Dysplasias.
The prevalence of skeletal dysplasias approximates 3 in 10,000 births.
Two groups account for more than half of all cases: the fibroblast growth factor 3 (FGFR3) chondrodysplasia group and the osteogenesis imperfecta and decreased bone density group.
Each occurs in 0.8 in 10,000 births .
Evaluation of a pregnancy with suspected skeletal dysplasia includes a survey of every long bone, as well as the hands and feet, skull size and shape, clavicles, scapulae, thorax, and spine.
Reference tables are used to determine which long bones are affected and ascertain the degree of shortening (Appendix, p. 1239).
Involvement of all long bones is termed micromelia, whereas predominant involvement of only the proximal, intermediate, or distal long bone segments is termed rhizomelia, mesomelia, and acromelia, respectively.
The degree of ossification should be noted, as should presence of bowing or fractures.
Although precise characterization may elude prenatal diagnosis, it is frequently possible to determine whether a skeletal dysplasia is lethal.
Lethal dysplasias show profound long bone shortening, often with measurements far below the 5th percentile, and display femur length-to-abdominal circumference ratios <16 percent (Nelson, 2014; Rahemtullah, 1997; Ramus, 1998).
Other sonographic abnormalities are generally evident.
Pulmonary hypoplasia is suggested by a thoracic circumference <80 percent of the abdominal circumference value, a thoracic circumference 50 percent of the thoracic circumference value (Appendix, p. 1238).
Affected pregnancies may also develop hydramnios and/or hydrops.
The FGFR3 chondrodysplasias include achondroplasia, hypochondroplasia, and thanatophoric dysplasia.
Achondroplasia is the most common nonlethal skeletal dysplasia.
An impressive 98 percent of cases are due to a specific point mutation in the FGFR3 gene.
Inheritance is autosomal dominant, and 80 percent of cases result from a new mutation.
Achondroplasia is characterized by long bone shortening that is predominantly rhizomelic, an enlarged head with frontal bossing, depressed nasal bridge, exaggerated lumbar lordosis, and a trident configuration of the hands.
Intelligence is usually normal.
The femur and humerus measurements may not fall below the 5th percentile until the early third trimester.
In homozygotes, who represent 25 percent of the offspring of heterozygous parents, the condition is characterized by greater long bone shortening and is lethal.
The other major class of FGFR3 dysplasias, thanatophoric dysplasia, is the most common lethal skeletal disorder.
It is characterized by severe micromelia, and affected fetuses—particularly those with type II—may develop a characteristic cloverleaf skull deformity (Kleeblattschädel) due to craniosynostosis.
Genetic testing is confirmatory.
Osteogenesis imperfecta represents a group of skeletal dysplasias typified by hypomineralization.
There are multiple types, and more than 90 percent of cases are characterized by a mutation in the COL1A1 or COL1A2 gene.
Type II, also called the perinatal form, is lethal.
The skull displays a profound lack of ossification, and gentle pressure on the maternal abdomen from the ultrasound transducer results in visible skull deformation .
Other features include multiple in-utero fractures and ribs that appear “beaded.
Inheritance is autosomal dominant, such that all cases result from either new mutations or gonadal mosaicism.
Another skeletal dysplasia that creates severe hypomineralization
is hypophosphatasia, which has an autosomal recessive inheritance.
Figure 15-63.
Post-axial polydactyly.
A. In this image of the hand, the arrow points to a rudimentary digit adjacent to the little finger.
B. Foot with 6 toes in a fetus with trisomy 13.
The arrow points to the extra digit.
# Polydactyly.
The most common skeletal abnormality is polydactyly, which occurs in approximately 1 in 1000 births.
It is post-axial if on the side of the ulna or fibula and pre-axial if on the side of the radius or tibia .
The extra digit is often rudimentary, and in the absence of a bony component, prenatal detection may be limited.
Post-axial polydactyly is more common and is frequently inherited in an autosomal dominant fashion.
Polydactyly is also a feature of syndromes such as Meckel-Gruber and trisomy 13.
Figure 15-64.
Osteogenesis imperfecta, Type IIa.
A. Due to lack of skull ossification, gentle ultrasound transducer pressure on the maternal abdomen results in visible deformation (flattening) of the skull in this 24-week fetus.
B. When the transducer pressure is removed, the skull shape returns to normal.
C. In the four-chamber view of the heart, in-utero fractures lead to abrupt angulation of the ribs (arrows).
D. The thorax is markedly smaller than the abdomen in this sagittal image.
# Clubfoot—Talipes Equinovarus.
This disorder is notable for a deformed talus and shortened Achilles tendon.
The affected foot is abnormally fixed and positioned with equinus (downward pointing), varus (inward rotation), and forefoot adduction.
Most cases are considered malformations, with a multifactorial genetic component.
However, an association with environmental factors and with early amniocentesis suggests that deformation also plays a role .
Sonographically, the footprint is visible in the same plane as the tibia and fibula .
Figure 15-65.
Talipes equinovarus or clubfoot.
This condition is diagnosed by visualizing the “footprint” in the same plane as the tibia and fibula.
The prevalence of clubfoot approximates 1 in 1000 births, and the male:female ratio is 2:1 (Carey, 2003; Pavone, 2012).
Clubfoot is bilateral in approximately 50 percent of cases.
At least 50 percent of affected individuals have associated abnormalities, such as neural-tube defects, arthrogryposis, and myotonic dystrophy and other genetic syndromes (Mammen, 2004; Sharma, 2011).
If there are other abnormalities, aneuploidy is present in 30 percent.
In contrast, the aneuploidy rate is <4 percent when clubfoot appears isolated (Lauson, 2010; Sharma, 2011).
Thus, a careful search for associated abnormalities is warranted, and chromosomal microarray analysis may be considered.
# Limb-Reduction Defects.
Documentation of the arms and legs is a component of the standard examination.
The absence or hypoplasia of all or part of one or more extremities is a limb-reduction defect.
The birth prevalence is 4 to 8 in 10,000 (Kucik, 2012; Stoll, 2010; Vasluian, 2013).
Approximately half of these are isolated defects, up to one third occur as part of a recognized syndrome, and individuals in the remaining cases have other coexisting anomalies (Stoll, 2010; Vasluian, 2013).
Upper extremities are affected more frequently than lower ones.
A terminal transverse limb defect lacks part or all of a distal limb to create a stump .
This is more common than a longitudinal defect, which is complete or partial absence of the long bone(s) on only one side of a given extremity.
Figure 15-66.
Transverse limb-reduction defect.
A. At 18 weeks’ gestation, only a rudimentary hand was visible.
B. By 24 weeks, the radius and ulna were normal in size and appearance, and small rudimentary digits were evident.
Absence of an entire extremity is termed amelia.
Phocomelia, associated with thalidomide exposure, is an absence of one or more long bones with the hands or feet attached to the trunk .
Limb-reduction defects are associated with numerous genetic syndromes, such as Roberts syndrome, an autosomal recessive condition characterized by tetraphocomelia.
A clubhand deformity, usually from an absent
radius, is a component of the thrombocytopenia-absent radius syndrome and is also associated with trisomy 18 (Fig. 16-5, p. 312).
Limb-reduction defects may occur in the setting of a disruption such as amnionic-band sequence .
They have also been associated with chorionic villus sampling when performed before 10 weeks’ gestation (Fig. 17-5, p. 346).